<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-inadarei-prefer-transclude-xml-01" category="info">

    <front>
        <title abbrev="Transclude for HTTP Prefer">Transclude Preference for the  Prefer Header for HTTP (RFC-7240)</title>
        <author initials='I.' surname="Nadareishvili" fullname='Irakli Nadareishvili'>
            <organization/>
            <address>
                <uri>http://freshblurbs.com</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date day="15" month="September" year="2016" />
        <abstract><t>The specification for Transclude preference is an extension to the  Prefer Header for HTTP <xref target="RFC7240" />. It works similar to other preferences defined in <xref target="RFC7240" />, such as: return, respond-async, wait and handling.</t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Note to Readers">
            <t>Please discuss this draft on the apps-discuss mailing list (<eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/apps-discuss"/>).</t>
            <t>Online access to all versions and files is available on GitHub (<eref target="https://github.com/inadarei/draft-prefer-transclude"/>).</t>
        </note>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Requirements notation">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>"Prefer Header for HTTP" <xref target="RFC7240" /> proposes an HTTP header that can be used to indicate that particular server behaviors are preferred by the client but are not required for successful completion of the request. It further defines several standard Preferences, such as the "return" preference. The "return" preference lets the server know that the client would prefer a specific representation of a resource in a response payload, e.g. full representation vs. a minimal one.</t>
            <t>Preferences like the "return" one are critical for mobile scenarios as mobile applications are very sensitive to network latency, throughput and anything that can improve end-user experience, even on resource-constrained networks. Prefer header allows servers to tune and optimize its response payload based on client preferences, for instance: to only send mobile app a minimal response when it doesn't need full resource.</t>
            <t>The size of the payload is not the only preference that can improve user-experience in mobile scenarios, however. Closely related to the size of the payload, is the number of HTTP requests a client needs to make to get all of the required data. This is the challenge that "transclude" preference addresses.</t>
            <t>When server sends hypermedia responses (e.g. in the case of Hypermedia APIs) some of the response data may be referenced via a URI link instead of being embedded in the payload itself. The need to grab data from a link can degrade experience of mobile applications, since they are forced to make multiple requests to per single end-user request. This is sometimes referred to as "chatty interface" and is a significant problem for mobile and Internet of Things scenarios.</t>
            <t>Transclude preference notifies the server that the client would prefer the server to proactively transclude certain content represented by links of indicated link relation types. The notion of "link relation type", in this context is as defined by <xref target="RFC5988" />.</t>
            <t>As a result of using a transclude preference, a client receives all of the required data already embedded in the response output, without the need to make additional network calls.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Transclude Usage Example" anchor="transclude-example">
        <figure>
            <preamble>
        Following is an example of a client asking server to transclude data represented at the copyright, edit-form and "other_form" links. Since "other_form" is not a standard, IANA link relation type, client is using a URI for identifying the link relation type.
            </preamble>
            <artwork>
    Get /blog/1223 HTTP/1.1
    Host: api.example.org
    Content-Type: application/json  
    Prefer: transclude=copyright,edit-form,http://rels.example.com/other_form
    Vary: Prefer,Accept,Accept-Encoding
            </artwork>
        </figure>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
        <t>None.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title='Normative References'>
            <reference anchor='RFC7240'>
                <front>
                <title>Prefer Header for HTTP (RFC-7240)</title>
                <author initials='J' surname='Snell' fullname='James Snell'>
                    <organization />
                </author>
                <date month='June' year='2014' />
                <abstract>
                    <t>This specification defines an HTTP header field that can be used by a client to request that certain behaviors be employed by a server while processing a request.</t>
                </abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7240" />
            </reference>      
            <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
                <front>
                <title>RFC-2119</title>
                <author initials='S' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
                    <organization />
                </author>
                <date month='March' year='1997' />
                <abstract>
                    <t>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels.</t>
                </abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
            </reference>
            <reference anchor='RFC5988'>
                <front>
                <title>Web Linking (RFC-5988)</title>
                <author initials='M' surname='Nottingham' fullname='Mark Nottingham'>
                    <organization />
                </author>
                <date month='October' year='2010' />
                <abstract>
                    <t>This document specifies relation types for Web links, and defines a registry for them.  It also defines the use of such links in HTTP headers with the Link header field.</t>
                </abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5988" />
            
            </reference>  
        </references>
    </back>

</rfc>
